Finding Aid for the Akahori Family papers, ca. 1908-1965 LSC.2010.01
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Office records of Akahori Horitsu Jimusho
  - Records on clients who sought assistance in legal matters at the Akahori Horitsu Jimusho
    - Applications for city liquor licenses for and related correspondence on 11 restaurant and grocery store operators in Terminal Island and adjacent areas., 1932 November-1933 May (Box 24, Folder 23)
  - Office records relating to the fishing industry in Terminal Island
    - Office reference copies of the Japanese government passport regulations and the U.S. immigration law and regulations, ca.1930-1933 (Box 24, Folder 24)
      Includes newspaper clippings on the Japanese immigration question.
    - Correspondence exchanged between Akahori and the law offices of Briney and Ekdale, proctors in admirality, in San Pedro, regarding Japanese fishermen in Terminal Island, 1932 April-1933 July (Box 24, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence exchanged between Akahori and agents of fishing companies, and documents related to the chartering of fishing boats for Terminal Island fishermen., 1932-1933 (Box 24, Folder 26)
      Correspondence are with agents Hansen & Rowland, Inc. and J.F. Gisler, as well as fishing boats owner John Skansi.
    - Correspondence with Albert K. Kempton, import/exporter, 1933 May-July (Box 24, Folder 27)
    - Insurance policy papers of Japanese fishermen in Terminal Island, 1932 September-1933 January (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence relating to the National Fisheries Co., San Francisco, 1932-1933 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Office records on Heisaku Inaba, fisherman, Terminal Island, 1932 January-1933 November (Box 25, Folder 3)
      Regarding Mariner's insurance policy; settlement of disputes with Toyo Fishing Co., Inc., San Pedro; insurance claims for damages caused by a marine accident; and the charter of a fishing boat at Tacoma, Washington.
    - Office records on Y. Kato and his crew, Terminal Island, 1932-1933 (Box 25, Folder 4)
      Regarding a settlement of disputes with Coast Fishing Co. and other canneries in Terminal Island.
    - Office records on Tetsumasa Miyagishima and his crew, 1932 September-December (Box 25, Folder 5)
      Regarding the charter of a fishing boat.
    - Office records on Akira Miyama, fisherman, Terminal Island, 1932 May-1933 April (Box 25, Folder 6)
      Regarding the charter of a fishing boat and claims for damages caused by a collision with a cargo vessel in the San Pedro Harbor.
    - Office records on Shigeichi Muramoto, fisherman, Terminal Island, 1932 August-1933 July (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Regarding the charter of fishing boats at Monterey and San Francisco, California, and Tacoma, Washington; and contract negotiatons with canneries.
    - Office records on K. Murata and his crew, Terminal Island, 1933 June (Box 25, Folder 8)
      Regarding the charter of a fishing boat named "Hermosa."
    - Office records on Shintaro Nakagawa, fisherman, Terminal Island, 1927 April-1933 March (Box 25, Folder 9)
      Regarding a settlement of disputes with investors over a mortgage payment, and the charter of fishing boats in Seattle and San Francisco.
    - Office records on A. Nakasuji and his fishing crew, Terminal Island, 1931 May-1933 May (Box 25, Folder 10)
      Regarding settlements of disputes with Martinac Ship Building Company in Tacoma, Washington, over a new ship ordered by the crew; and negotiations on the charter of a fishing boat.
    - Office records on Sanyo Trading Company, Los Angeles, 1932 August-September (Box 25, Folder 11)
      Regarding the tuna canning business.
    - Office records on Kurakichi Shimizu, fisherman, San Pedro, 1932 January-1933 January (Box 25, Folder 12)
      Regarding the building of a new fishing boat by Martinac Ship Building Company in Tacoma, Washington, and disputes with the company over financial matters.
    - Office records on Sotaro Shinji and Kenichi Tsuchiya, fishermen, Terminal Island, 1933 April-July (Box 25, Folder 13)
      Regarding financial difficulties and bankruptcy.
    - Office records on Kumaichi Takeoka, fisherman, Monterey, 1933 February-March (Box 25, Folder 14)
      Regarding the hiring of a diver.
    - Office records on Asagoro Yoshioka and his crew, Terminal Island, 1932 December-1933 January (Box 25, Folder 15)
      Regarding financial matters.
  - Office records relating to the Akahori Collection Agency
    - Official documents regarding the startup of the Akahori Collection Agency, 1930 (Box 25, Folder 16)
    - Office records on N. Abe & Co., wholesale produce merchant, Honolulu, Hawaii (debtor), ca.1928-1931 (Box 25, Folder 17)
      Regarding the collection of a personal loan in the amnount of $500, through the Kawasaki Office in Hilo, Hawaii.
    - Office records on S. Amasuga, 1931 August-September (Box 25, Folder 18)
    - Office records on Al Fletcher, collection agent, Long Beach, 1930 August-1931 August (Box 25, Folder 19)
      Regarding the collection from Japanese debtors, totalling approximately $2000.
    - Office records on Y. Fujita, 1929 April-1930 March (Box 25, Folder 20)
    - Office records on K. Furutani, service station owner, Terminal Island (creditor), 1932 October (Box 25, Folder 21)
      Regarding unpaid bills.
    - Office records on Gardena Lumber Co., Gardena (creditor), 1928 October-1930 December (Box 25, Folder 22)
      Regarding unpaid bills of Japanese customers, amounting to approximately $1300.
    - Office records on Ethel M. Gifford, collection agent, Long Beach, 1933 February-June (Box 25, Folder 23)
      Regarding a collection from Japanese debtors in the amount of $180.
    - Office records on K. Hamada and other Japanese investors, Los Angeles, 1933 January (Box 25, Folder 24)
      Regarding the recovery of invested funds totalling $31,417.
    - Office records on Hara, 1928-1929 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Office records on Takejio Hari, Tacoma, Washington, 1931-1933 July (Box 26, Folder 2)
      Regarding a collection on a personal loan in the amount of $150.
    - Office records on Hashimoto Company, wholesale dealer in fishermen's supplies, Terminal Island (creditor), 1931 November-1932 December (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Office records on Hayashi Floral Company, Hollywood (debtor), 1929 May (Box 26, Folder 4)
      Regarding a collection referred by the Acme Adjusting Association, Los Angeles, in the amount of $378.
    - Office records on Isekichi Hayashikawa, Terminal Island (debtor), 1932 November-1933 July (Box 26, Folder 5)
      Regarding a personal loan of $1250 and repayment schedule.
    - Office records on Frank Hidaka, Los Angeles (debtor), 1930 March-1931 June (Box 26, Folder 6)
      Regarding unpaid medical bills in 1928.
    - Office records on J. Hirota and others, Los Angeles (creditors), 1930 (Box 26, Folder 7)
      Regarding the recovery of invested funds from Kisaburo Hatanaka, manager of a pig farm in Long beach, who misappropriated investors' money reported to amount to about $51,000.
    - Office records on Inglewood Mercantile Company (creditor), 1929 June-1930 May (Box 26, Folder 8)
      Regarding the unpaid bills of Japanese customers, amounting to approximately $850.
    - Office records on M. Ishii, 1932 May-July (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Office records on H. Isomura and H. Morioka, fishermen, Terminal Island (creditors), 1932 September (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Office records on Masao Itano, interpreter and insurance agent, Sacramento, 1932 April (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Office records on Kichinosuke Iwashige, Los Angeles (debtor), 1931 November-1933 December (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Office records on Yasujiro Iwata, farmer, San Francisco (debtor), 1925 Deember-1931 August (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Office records on Kanzo Izumi, ca.1929 August-1930 July (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Office records on I.H.Kakishita, fisherman, Terminal Island (debtor), 1933 February (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Office records on K. Kamitaki, ca.1930 June-July (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Office records on Taro Kanemoto, farmer, Montebello (debtor), 1932 October-1933 January (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Office records on Tokuyoshi Katayama, proprietor if Tokyo Hotel, Los Angeles (creditor), 1932 February-September (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Office records on Y. Kawabata, ca.1933 February-May (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Office records on Takeo Kiyota, proprietor of I&I Produce Co., Los Angeles (creditor), 1927 December-1931 December (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Office records on T. Kobata, fisherman, Terminal Island (debtor), 1932 November-1933 May (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Office records on J. Kohara, 1933 August (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - Office records on M. Koyama, 1933 January (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - Office records on I. Kuga, ca.1933 May (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - Office records on B. Maeda, 1932 December (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - Office records on Yozo Maeda, farmer, Chatsworth (debtor), 1927 August-1928 November (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - Office records on Jiro Masuda, Mt. View (creditor), 1930 October-1933 December (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - Office records on Masukawa, 1933 April (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - Office records on Torasaku Mikuriya, West Los Angeles (debtor), 1933 August (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - Office records on J.K. Miyaji, 1929 June (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - Office records on Shinkichi Miyoshi, Terminal Island (debtor), 1931 April-1933 June (Box 26, Folder 31)
    - Office records on D. Murata, Los Angeles (creditor), 1930 March-May (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - Office records on Nakamoto, produce shipper, Calexico (debtor), 1927 September-1928 July (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Office records on Akimatsu Nakamura, proprietor of A. Nakamura Co., general merchandise store, Terminal Island (creditor), 1933 May-July (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - Office records on M. Nakamura, Los Angeles (debtor), ca.1929-1931 June (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - Office records on K. Nakayama, owner of Paradise Florist, Los Angeles (debtor), 1930 April-October (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - Office records on S. Nakazawa, 1932 July-October (Box 26, Folder 37)
    - Office records on T. Oda, 1931 November (Box 26, Folder 38)
    - Office records on Okumura, 1932 (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - Office records on F.Y. Otsuka, 1930 July-October (Box 26, Folder 40)
    - Office records on Ozawa, 1932 December (Box 26, Folder 41)
    - Office records on Jack Pole, 1932 October-December (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - Office records on Sakagami, undated (Box 26, Folder 43)
    - Office records on Sakauye, 1930 July-August (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Office records on A. Sano, 1929-1931 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Office records on Taro Shiba, M.D., Terminal Island (creditor and debtor), 1932 October-November (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Office records on Umekichi Shibanaka, undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Office records on Shibata, 1931 February-August (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Office records on Ryoen Shimanouchi, journalist, Los Angeles (debtor), 1929 January-1930 January (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Office records on F.S. Shimegi, 1931 February-August (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Office records on T. Shindo, Terminal Island, 1932 September-1933 July (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Office records on A.G. Snow, 1927 September (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Office records on K. Suzuki, 1931 August (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Office records on G.K. Takeda, gardener, Los Angeles (creditor), 1930 May-1931 August (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Office records on Ichisuke Taniguchi, fisherman, Terminal Island (creditor), 1933 May-August (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Office records on Tanimoto, 1930 March-1931 August (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Office records on K. Tsuji, 1928 January-February (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Office records on H. Uchino, 1930 February-1931 August (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Office records on Shige Ueno, proprietor of Showa Hotel, Los Angeles (creditor), 1929-1933 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Office records on Uyeshima, 1930 April-July (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Office records on J. Watanabe, 1930 July (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Office records on Tom Watanabe, 1933 January-August (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - Office records on H.C. Westover, 1933 August (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Office records on S.H. Yamamoto, 1932 August-1933 May (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Office records on R. Yano, proprietor of Hollywood Wholesale Produce Co., and Nippon Art Goods Co., Los Angeles (creditor), 1931 Septemer-November (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Office records on Yoshida, 1929 July-1930 July (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Office records on S.I. Yoshii, 1930 June (Box 27, Folder 24)
- Stone Chemical Products Company
  Akahori purchased the Stone Chemical Products Company along with two other Isseis in July 1926 as a business interest. The outcome of this venture is unknown.
  - "Report on Books and Accounts of the Stone Chemical Products Company", 1926 September 30 (Box 27, Folder 25)
- American Oriental Advertising Company (AOC)
  While still holding his Horitsu Jimusho, Akahori also entered business dealings with the American Oriental Advertising Company (AOC) in Hollywood. This proved to be an especially costly mistake as his entanglement with its chief Japanese investor, Y.K. Yamamoti, over financial matters, resulted in his abscondence from the Japanese community in Terminal Island, California to Seattle, Washington. Included in the series are business correspondence, records of both personal and business expenses, as well as legal paperwork.
  - Minutes of various meetings before and after the incorporation of the AOC, 1931 (Box 27, Folder 26)
  - Certificate of incorporation from the state of Delaware, 1931 July 29 (Box 27, Folder 27)
  - Business correspondence relating to the AOC, 1931 April-1932 September (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence regarding Teruo K. Takimoto, prinicpal investor, 1929 December-1932 April (Box 27, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence regarding the proposed publication of the Japanese edition of "The Olympiad California", 1931 November-1932 February (Box 27, Folder 30)
    In commemoration of the upcoming 1932 Summer Olympics held in Los Angeles.
  - Documents relating to the proposed idea of advertising on trash cans, 1931 April-September (Box 27, Folder 31)
    In English and Spanish.
  - A stenographer's notebook, 1931 (Box 27, Folder 32)
  - Life insurance policies of the AOC, 1931 (Box 27, Folder 33)
  - Financial statements of the AOC, 1931 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    Includes bank statements, notes, and records of checks issued.
  - Cancelled checks, 1931 (Box 28, Folder 2)
  - Detailed and extensive reports with exhibits on the AOC, written by Akahori, 1931 April-September
    - Report #1 with exhibits, 1931 April (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Report #2 with exhibits, 1931 May (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Report #3 with exhibits, 1931 June (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Report #4 with exhibits, 1931 July (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Report #5 with exhibits, 1931 August (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Report #6 with exhibits, 1931 September (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and notes relating to an extortion allegedly committed against Akahori by his creditor in Terminal Island, and his escape to and subsequent resettlement in Seattle., 1931 September-1934 July (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Reports and notes documenting Akahori's arrest on charges of grand theft and forgery., 1932 March (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Court papers, notes, and clippings on claims filed by Akahori against E.E. Violette., 1932 March (Box 29, Folder 2)
    For unpaid wages amounting to $1,808.10.
- Hyoroku Oishi Office
  Akahori opened the Hyoroku Oishi Office in Seattle after fleeing from Terminal Island, using one of his aliases, providing similar services as he did at his Horitsu Jimusho. He ran this office from 1931 to 1941.
  - Correspondence, notes, and financial records of the Hyoroku Oishi Office., 1934-1941 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Records on Yoshikawa Torakichi, proprietor of T. Yoshikawa Co., Seattle, Washington., 1934 February-1940 September (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Akahori made business arrangements and negotiations for the company.
  - Documents and correspondence on the charter of fishing boats for Japanese fishermen in Seattle, Washington, and Terminal Island, California., ca.1935-1938 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Notes, statements, and reports on the charter of a fishing baot, Garnet C, by Akahori for albacore fishing off the Oregon-Washington coast., 1938 August-1939 February (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Sales materials for Insurance Investors Fund, Inc., 1937 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    The Hyoroku Oishi Office was the sole agent of the company for Japanese communities.
  - Office records on 11 clients, 1934-1941 (Box 29, Folder 8)
- Columbia Commerical Company
  Akahori founded the Columbia Commercial Company, a fisheries trading business which also served as a publisher, in conjunction with the Hyoroku Oishi Office from 1934 to 1941.
  - Business correspondence, 1934 August-1941 September (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Notes, financial records, and product sample, ca.1938 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Records on the various publications of the Columbia Commercial Company, 1934-1941 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    Publications include "Beikoku kishinroku" [characters] [Who's Who in America], 1934; Japanese telephone directory: Seattle and vicinity, 1938; "Jinji koshinroku: dai juni han" [characters] [Who's Who of Japanese, no.12], 1941; and "Koronbia Shoho" [characters] [The Colombia Commercial News], 1941.
- Wartime internment
  - Internment diaries
    - Akahori's "An Internee's Diary.", 1942 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Akahori's internment camp diary., 1945 November 4-1946 February 10 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      With photocopy.
  - Personal records
    - Biographical notes written by Akahori in internment camps., 1941-1943 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Petitions for Akahori's release from internment and related documents., 1943 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Documents regarding Akahori's postwar repatriation hearings., 1945 November-1946 April (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Petitions for the family reunion of internees at Crystal City, Texas., ca.1943 September (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - War Relocation Authority (WRA) forms used at Fort Missoula, Lordburg, Santa Fe, and Crystal City., 1942 February-1945 February (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Documents on the shipment, storage and disposition of the properties belonging to the Akahoris during internment., 1942 June-1946 April (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Internment correspondence
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1941 February-March (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1941 December 11-December 26 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1941 December 28-1942 June 22 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1942 June 26-1943 June 1 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1943 June 22-1944 February 22 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1941 December 25-1942 July 4 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1942 July 12-1943 August 25 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Akahori's correspondence to his wife and daughter during internment., 1943 September 1-1944 February 24 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence between Akahori and his friends during his internment., 1942 March 24-1944 March 1 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence between Akahori and his friends during his internment., 1945 October-1946 May (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Masaru's lecture outlines
    - Outlines prepared by Akahori for a series of lectures on current world affairs, given at Santa Fe and Crystal City (1 of 2)., 1943 December-1944 September (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Includes draft outlines for 25 lectures, mostly undated. His earlier lectures on the current war between the U.S. and Japan delivered at Santa Fe in 1943 were published in outline form as "Heiwa to senso" [characters] [Peace and War].
    - Outlines prepared by Akahori for a series of lectures on current world affairs, given at Santa Fe and Crystal City (2 of 2)., 1943 December-1944 September (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City, 1944 December 31-1945 March 25 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City, 1945 April 8-29 (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City, 1945 May 6-27 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City, 1945 June 3-25 (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City, 1945 July 1-29 (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City, 1945 August 5-26 (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City (1 of 2), ca.1944 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Outlines for Akahori's "Nichiyo jiji kaisetsu" [characters] [Sunday news commentaries on current phases of the war in the Pacific and European theaters] at Crystal City (2 of 2), ca.1944 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Outlines for 12 lectures given by Akahori on various topics., ca.1944 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Lordsburg
    - A collection of weeds and plants in and around the Lordsburg Internment Camp, 1942 June-July (Box 33, Folder 4)
      2 notebooks.
    - Draft notes for Akahori's news broadcast programs on radio in the Lordsburg Internment Camp, 1942 July 23-1942 August 19 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Copies of letters drafted by Akahori for the Lordsburg Camp spokesperson, 1943 January and March (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Akahori's memos from Lordsburg, ca.1943 February (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Kenji Kasai, "Rozubagu jiho no naiyo to jiho dojin no shosoku" [characters] [The Lordsburg Times and its staff members], 1943 (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Publications by the Lordsburg internees, 1942 October, 1943 January, undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Akahori's notes on a series of lectures delivered by Shuichi Watanabe, fellow internee, on English grammar at Lordsburg, 1942 December 17-1943 June 8 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Minidoka
    - Typewritten copies of Father Joseph Kitagawa's sermon given at the Church of the Holy Apostles at the Minidoka Internment Camp, Hunt Idaho, 1943 March-April (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Santa Fe
    - "Heiwa to senso" [characters] [Peace and war], 1943 March-April (Box 34, Folder 3)
      A series of lectures on American history given by Akahori in the Santa Fe Internment Camp. Includes his memos and notes regarding its publication in the camp.
    - Manuscripts of essays written in the Santa Fe Camp, 1944 February (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Santa Fe nihonjin shyosho jinmeiroku [characters] [Roster of Japanese internees at Santa Fe], 1943 November 1 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Santa Fe Bukkyo Renmei [characters] [Santa Fe Buddhist Association], "Reihai seiten" [characters] [Buddhist scriptures and hymns], 1943 (Box 34, Folder 6)